Inventory of the Barker-Cooke Papers 1809-1889
Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Special Collections, College of William and Mary
Barker-Cooke Papers, 1809-1889.
Special Collections, College of William and Mary
Mss. 65 B24
182 items.
Letters and business papers, chiefly 1848-1866, of James E. Cooke of Powhatan, Virginia and the Barker family of Fluvanna County, Virginia.
Barker Family,; James E. Cooke.
Administrative Information
Restrictions on Access
Collection is open to all researchers.
Acquisition Information
Purchased; 1940.
Scope and Content
Letters and business papers, chiefly 1848-1866, of James E. Cooke of Powhatan, Virginia and the Barker family of Fluvanna County, Virginia including letters relating to the hiring out of slaves, plantation operations and the Civil War (letters of John H. Barker and Henry J. Dobbs of the 18th Virginia Regiment of the Confederate army concerning the Battle of First Bull Run (Manassas).
Organization
The collection has been divided into series with Series 1 covering letters and Series 2 including accounts, receipts and notes. The subseries under letters is grouped by date: Subseries 1 are letters 1848- 1854, Subseries 2 are the Civil War letters and Subseries 3 covers letters written after the Civil War.
Index Terms
Family Names:
Barker Family
Persons:
Cooke, James E. fl. 1848-1853; Barker, John H.; Dobbs, Henry J.
Subjects:
Slave labor -- Virginia; Slavery -- Virginia -- History -- 19th century; Plantation life -- Virginia -- History -- 19th century; Bull Run, 1st Battle of, Va., 1861.
Corporate Names:
Confederate States of America. Army. Virginia Infantry Regiment, 18th.; Confederate States of America. Army. Virginia Infantry Regiment, 13th.
Geographical Names:
Powhatan County (Va.); Fluvanna County (Va.)
Contents List and Descriptions
  Series 1: Letters and Poem
- Letters and Poem, 1848-1889.
  Correspondence of James E. Cooke and the Barker family.
  - Plantation Letters, 1848-1853.
    - [?] to [James E. ?] Cooke, 2 February 1848., 1 item. (Folder 1)
      Detailed instructions for plantation operations.
    - Hez[ekiah] Ford, Cumberland Court House, Virginia to James E. Cooke, at Jefferson, Virginia,; Sublett's Tavern, Powhatan, Virginia, Black Heath, Virginia and Hallsboro, Virginia, 1848-1853., 13 items. (Folder 2)
      Letters concerning hiring out to others of slaves belonging to Cooke.
  - Miscellaneous Letters, 1852-1854., 4 items.
    - Thos. P. Nash, Powhatan, to [James E.] Cooke., 1 item. (Folder 3)
    - E. J. [?] Rapp[a]h[annock] Academy to [?], 11 February 1853., 1 item. (Folder 3)
    - H. Gordon, Ballsville to James E. Cook[e], Powhatan, 24 June 1853., 1 item (Folder 3)
    - J. S. Cooke to [?], 7 February 1854., 1 item. (Folder 3)
  - Civil War Letters, 1861-1865.
    - John H. Barker, Camp near Centerville to sister Miss Mildred A. Barker, 28 July 1861., 1 item. (Folder 4)
    - Henry J. Dobbs, Camp near Centerfield to Millie and Patty [Barker], 7 August 1861., 1 item. (Folder 4)
      Includes 8 August 1861 to sister M. J. Barker
    - H[enry] J. Dobbs, Camp near Centerville, to Millie and Pattie [Barker], 7 February 1862., 1 item. (Folder 4)
      Includes letter of John H. Barker to sisters Millie and Pattie [Barker].
    - John H. Barker, Richmond to brother Charles [Barker], 20 June 1862., 1 item. (Folder 4)
    - John H. Barker, Camp of Garnett's Brigade to sister Millie [Barker], 10 February 1863., 1 item. (Folder 4)
    - Henry [?], Camp 18th Virginia, to Millie [Barker], 4 February 1865., 1 item. (Folder 4)
  - Letters, 1866 and 1889 and Poem 1866-1889, 3 items.
    - Jennie Hudgens, Locust Grove, Cumberland, Virginia to Millie A. Barker, 28 March 1866., 1 item (Folder 5)
    - Jennie Hudgens, Cumberland, Virginia, to Millie [A. Barker], 24 June 1866., 1 item. (Folder 5)
    - Poem from [?], For Miss Patty Barker 13 December 1889., 1 item. (Folder 5)
  Series 2: Accounts, Receipts, and Notes
- Accounts, Receipts, and Notes, 1809-1882.
  - Accounts, receipts, and notes, 1809-1820., 6 items. (Folder 6)
  - Accounts, receipts, and notes 1821-1824., 15 items. (Folder 7)
  - Accounts, receipts, and notes 1825-1829., 13 items. (Folder 8)
  - Accounts, receipts, and notes 1830-1833., 20 items. (Folder 9)
  - Accounts, receipts, and notes 1834-1839., 15 items. (Folder 10)
  - Accounts, receipts, and notes 1840-1845., 15 items. (Folder 11)
  - Accounts, receipts, and notes 1846-1849., 28 items. (Folder 12)
  - Accounts, receipts, and notes 1850-1852., 22 items. (Folder 13)
  - Accounts, receipts, and notes 1853-1882, n.d., 20 items. (Folder 14)